There we go. Yay. All right. So my name is
Scott Perry. I'm here to talk about open
standards and open protocols. And so when
you're looking at a SEDI project, okay,
we're just getting started, but there's
been effort to deal with decentralized
identity for the last 20 years, starting
with Phil Windley co-chairing the Internet
Identity Workshop 20 years ago. And then
for me, it's been 10 years after I got a
call from Timothy Ruff saying, I need help
around trying to deal with internet trust.
And I realized as an auditor that was
auditing certification authorities, I
realized that the traditional model wasn't
going to work to add internet, to add the
kind of trust that we're trying to do with
the SEDI project. So just a quick little
bit about me. I'm the auditor in the room.
I was auditing for my career. Last 20
years, I've been auditing cryptography as
a profession. Auditing small group folks
that audit certification authorities. I
was the auditor for a certification
authority based in Utah. It's great to be
back here. I was working with DigiSearch
for quite a long time. And I've also been
leading some open source and open
standards projects. projects that are
listed here, but I want to focus on the
acronym suit that I'm going to talk about
because it's important for folks to
understand there has been a lot of work.
There was a question around, is it going
to work today? I'd say two years ago,
things hadn't been completely baked in,
but I think we're ready. The open source
community is absolutely ready for SEDI and
I'm excited for them to demonstrate their
value in all of the work that that they've
been doing for over 10 years. And so when
we start about that, I'm going to give you
just a summary of some of the
organizations that I've been touched with
that have been developing some unique
products that can be leveraged into the
SEDI project. And it starts with the Linux
Foundation. So I don't know if you know,
but the Linux Foundation is the largest
repository of open source code in the
world. They operate 100% of all the
supercomputers and 62.7 of servers run the
Linux kernel. And so they decided to get
involved in decentralized trust. There was
a number of projects that was driving some
of this type of thinking. And so they
established a subset of their organization
last year and they invited and
consolidated a couple of open source and
open standards projects. One that is
called the Trust over IP and I'd invite
all of you to spend time going to the
Trust over IP. I am the co-chair of the
steering committee. We have a couple of
steering committee members here in the
audience and they've been doing enormous
work to get ready for the SEDI project.
We've created a stack, a technology and a
governance stack. Everyone's talking about
governance. Trust over IP is the leading
organization driving governance standards
and methodologies and toolkits. And I hope
that the organization here, the SEDI
projects uses it because it's been
successful in the C2PA, in GLEIF, in the
government of Bhutan and such. It also is
housing KERI. You've heard some stories
about KERI. It's a blueprint of how to
decentralize identity and make security
more autonomous and user controlled. It's
exactly one of the main principles within
the SEDI project. We have a trust spanning
protocol which acts underneath the
internet protocol to the ability to
authenticate senders and payloads of
transactions because we need that level of
trust in our transaction protocols and
also it is leading around trust registries
which are public repositories of those
that have passed certain governance
frameworks. The Open Wallet Foundation was
founded in August 2023. It hosts
components that can be used to create
secure, flexible, and portable wallets.
Where are we going to keep the SEDI
credentials? We need a secure place
because they have private cryptographic
keys. Also, we've talked about the W3C
started in 1994, produces two key
standards that we can leverage within the
SEDI project. The decentralized
identifiers, the DIDS projects, as well as
defining the components of verifiable
credentials which we expect to use. In the
decentralized identity foundation started
in 2017, we have a number of projects that
are working that can add value. They are
the leading place to deal with all of the
decentralized identity methods that are
out in the marketplace and they are
working to consolidate that. They're
creating standards around the
communication using DIDCOM as well as the
presentation exchange of credentials as
well as hosting an organization called the
Creators Assertion Working Group which I
co-chair which deals with individual and
organizational attribution to any digital
object based on the content credential
created by the C2PA. So I would look that
up as well. Also the OpenID which has been
around since 2007 and has modified their
standards to deal with verifiable
credentials with OpenID Connect and OpenID
verifiable credentials. ISO as we have
mentioned here has been instrumental in
creating foundational security standards
both with quality and ISO 27001 for for
foundational security management systems
as well as they have identity management
standard ISO 24760 and finally also the
mobile driver's license the ISO 18018013.
We talked a little bit about what the role
of the federal government would be. Well,
NIST is providing a lot of value there
associated with dealing with post-quantum
cryptography. They're also dealing with
the certification of hardware security
modules which protect your private key and
are the leading standard for digital
identity guidelines both for proofing of
identity, authentication, and federation.
So what's the case for open standards? How
do you use it? Okay. At the end of the
day, it enhances interoperability and
compatibility. accessibility. Okay? It
prevents the vendor lock-in so that all
the tech vendors are using open standards
and they can use it so you're not locked
into an individual technology company and
can't get out of them. It creates the
innovation and collaboration. You're not
limited to an individual's company, R&D.
You're leveraging world R&D. And that's
what the state of the organizations that I
work for, they are creating that research
and development that we could leverage. It
increases flexibility and Joe Jackson to
mention about future proofing. They're
baking in advances of these standards to
deal with new technologies as they come
along and they're free. State loves free,
right? And the best way to leverage it is
steal. this technology and steal these
standards because it's there for the
taking and they work. So I'm going to just
walk through I'm not going to go into
details of some of the products that we've
created in the open standards world but
these are the some of the ones as a
governance you know professional have
leveraged on and you know we've realized
there was a trust you know triangle with
the issuer holder and verifier trust over
IP added a governance model and we have
found that that's the missing, that's the
secret sauce into making it long-lasting
and workable. This, I'm not going to go
into the detail, but this is the trust
over IP trust stack. And you can see that
there's been a lot of work that's gone
into it. And Chris Ramel said to me, if
you do one thing, let people know how
complicated it is. And we've done a lot of
the baked in work. So governance
framework, it's already built. the
framework's work. You don't have to worry
about it. You just have to put in your
requirements into the governance framework
and then you could leverage the time and
energy to get this to market. So I'm going
to quickly go through the reasons why you
should adopt open standards.
It's all there and I think we're ready to
go and I think you could take advantage of
a lot of the work that's been done to make
this happen. If you want to have an idea
of a white paper that's free to use on how
to use governance and use trust
registries. I put it out there. It'll be
in the videotape so that you could access
this at your leisure. Thank you very much
for your time.